hey everyone welcome back to another
lesson in this tosca automation course
today we are going to see how we can
create our first test case in the tosca
commander
so let's get started
the first step in order to do this we
need to create a project right so that
will be our project and our own
workspace where we will create
all our
test cases our modules um or whatever is
required for that particular project
okay
so
go here in the dashboard you will see a
create new option right so click that
and you can select any repository if
none then it will create a single user
workspace okay
uh so we'll go ahead with that uh
it will take up a default folder
location
and now we need to give it a name right
so we'll give it
training
and we'll give it training project okay
we'll also use a workspace template now
these templates are provided by default
uh by tosca right which contains some
default test cases some default modules
which you can use in your projects so
it's always recommended to use this it
so once you select this use workspace
template it will be pre-loaded with this
standard dot tsu template right which is
um
it's present in your uh tosca directory
right so under c directory you will see
there is tosca underscore projects and
under this you will have common
repositories workspaces and the tasker
commander
okay
so under tosca commander you will see
there is standard dot tsu right so
that's the format of
any standard template okay
so
you can go ahead and select that if it
is not displayed here right so that
would be our standard template which
contains some modules which will be
required in our project
so click on ok to create our new
workspace
now
tosca will start creating this workspace
and it will do all some background tasks
right
after that
it is going to
enter into the tosca commander where you
can create your test cases by using
modules or test case design or
uh execute your test cases so all the
modules are now present in this tasker
commander
window right so we have already seen uh
we have uh seen how the tosca commander
works what are the different parts of
toska commander right but now we are
going to see how we can actually
create automation test cases inside our
task
okay
so these are the different sections um
right so we have talked about them
briefly we are in the test cases section
where we can create different test cases
right so these are pre-loaded with some
examples and some folders
but um
we'll for now we'll ignore them because
we are going to create our own right so
let's go ahead and create a folder here
right so you can either
create it by going here or you can also
type control n which is the shortcut
right
so uh we need to give it a name right so
for this demo purpose i am going to use
this particular page right it's a demo
application
by source labs so
it has got a login page and then some
products are displayed on the home page
right so our test case is pretty simple
we are just going to enter the username
password click on login and then it will
enter into the home page right so that's
our test case
so um
i'm going to create a folder for this
particular test scenario right so i'm
going to call it source demo
test
okay
so this is uh this is my folder inside
this i will have either subfolders or
test cases now it completely depends on
you how you want to design your test
case right so i will have one folder
which will i'll call it prerequisites
now i will tell you why i have created
this and what it will contain right
after this i will create a test case
okay again you can go through this menu
or you can use the shortcuts which is
displayed here okay
so this is my test case and i'm going to
call it login test
okay so this is my first test case
now
that's our test cases section right but
these are only uh you can create either
the folders subfolders or test cases
right
but the actual um object creation
happens in the module section right so
this is where you can scan your
application and get all the technical
information in order to drive your test
cases okay
so here also we need to create another
folder
uh which will contain all our technical
information or and other terms you can
also call them your page objects right
so these are the web elements which are
present in your page
and toska will scan that page or
application and get all the technical
information based on which it can
interact with those web elements right
so that's how you do automation any
particular tool right you get the
properties of those elements and then
you perform the actions on those
particular elements tosca is making the
job easier because it has got this
uh scan which can scan the application
and get all the elements and the
properties for you okay and store them
in a module
so let's create a module for our
application and we'll call it source
demo right so that's our module
now inside this uh module we need to
scan our application right so either you
can right click and
click on this scan drop down which
contains different kinds of applications
right so either it's a web application
api a mobile
a pdf remote terminal or you can also go
with webdriver salesforce file scan
legacy scan right so these are
different kinds of scanning technologies
which are available with
tosca through which you can scan
different applications right so since we
are working with the web application
we'll select the application
right
now this uh will now start the x scan
agent right which will basically scan
all the applications which are opened in
your windows okay
so you can see there are different
applications but i want to uh scan
the application which is open in google
chrome so select that
right and click on scan
now it will start scanning this
particular page right so it is asking
you to click on controls in your
application to add them right
so
i can click on username because i need
that i need password i need login button
right so as you can see these are the
three elements which have been selected
by me right
and if i expand this window you will see
uh there is the advanced section there
is the close window
you can also save it okay
so let's save um our elements okay
and i will look at the advanced section
later on where you can basically make
some changes to your element properties
right if they are not unique you can
select some other unique property
but for now let's uh
leave it as it is
so now you will see there is a module
which has been added here right and you
would like to basically change this
module name we'll call it login page
because uh it needs to be
more generic right so
anybody looking at this module can
understand
what is contained inside this module
right so it is a login page so we'll
name it as the login page right
now if you expand this module you will
see there is the username field there is
password that is login right and there
are different actions or value range you
can see
and then in the properties section you
will see all the different properties
are listed down here through which it is
able to identify these elements but you
don't need to worry about them tosca is
taking care of that right so
until all your objects are unique on the
page you don't need to worry about
changing anything
but if there are elements which are
which toska is not able to uniquely
identify then maybe
you have to add some more properties or
change some property values right
so we'll do that in later stages
but this is our module
now what we need to do we have got the
module we have got the test case now we
need to join this right uh we need to
somehow use this module uh inside our
test case because that is what will be
driving our test case right
so um if you want to view
different sections together right so
tosca provides you a way of doing that
now i want to see my module as well as
my test case right so drag that modules
window
and you will see here there are
different uh
sides where you can put this right so
you can put it in center
on top on bottom on left or right right
so let's put it on the right section
and you will see there will be two
windows now right so i can see two
windows together uh one side i will see
my modules one side i will see my test
cases or some other section right
so this way it is easy to actually uh
design your test cases along with the
modules which you are going to select
right
so um our login test requires a module
because
that is what it will drive our login
test right so
what we'll do we'll drag this module and
we'll put it in our login test
so that will create different steps for
our login test case so that is how you
design your test case you scan your
application get the module right and
then use that module or any number of
modules inside your test case now
depending on the scenario i can use
different modules inside my test case
okay
so as you can see it uh has got some
values right it requires some values in
order to enter a username a password or
it needs to perform some action okay so
that is where you have to enter a value
or you have to select a action mode
right there is also a data type as you
can see so data type is string
for password it is password for login it
is string okay
so
here what we are going to do we are
going to pass a value right a valid
username so i'm going to do that
okay um
so once the modules uh section is done
with right i can close that so that i
can view my test cases in a
proper way
right now this is the value i want to
enter um in my application right and
then i want to enter the password
so once you type the password
it will be converted into the password
format right which
you cannot see
um
then in the login so this is a button
it's not a text box right so you need to
take care of these things when you are
designing your test case okay so if it
is a text box right action mode is input
right so that means you're going to
enter something into that particular
element
but if it is a login
button right so you need to click on
that so you can go here and you can
select this drop down you will see there
is a click option
okay
so once you do that
even though the action mode is input
the value is the click
okay so this is a kind of action which
will be performed on this particular
button
okay
so that's uh that's our test case it
will basically enter the information and
perform all the operations on the
different elements
present inside this test case
okay
now we also have got a prerequisites
and we also require something called
now we cannot directly uh go ahead and
enter these right um tosca needs to open
that application and then it has to be
opened in a browser so where where are
these things happening right so we
haven't done that
so uh go to the
parent folder right so which is our
source demo test and here right click
and then
on the drop down you will find an option
called create test configuration
parameter okay
so click on that
so for our source demo test there will
be a
parameter which will be nothing but our
browser okay so if you click on this
drop down or you just type it
browser right you will see there is an
option for
the browser so this is a test
configuration parameter type
present in tosca and it has got some
values which are nothing but your
browser values okay so i'm going to use
chrome so i'll select chrome
i don't need to change the data type it
is string right so there are different
uh
test parameter configuration parameters
which you can add depending on what test
case you are designing but for my case
it is only the browser okay
so that's our test configuration
parameter and then
in prerequisites
now we have got a browser but we haven't
opened our application right so before
even going into the test case i need to
open
i need to go to that login page right so
that will happen in prerequisites
okay
so
um what we are going to do in
prerequisites is we are going to pick up
a module here okay
now there are different ways of doing it
again you can go to the module section
and drag it here right
or
you can press ctrl t
and it will show you
different modules which are required
or which you can put in your
prerequisites folder okay so
let's uh open our module section and now
you can see it is not here because i
close that section right but if you
want it back right
you can very well do that
so
okay so uh in the home uh in section you
will see there are all the sections
which are present here right so just
select the module section
and the module section would be back
right so let's put it on the right hand
side
and now we are going to use those
standard modules which are part of our
standard template right so these are
provided
by tosca to make our job easier right
now um
let's search what we are looking for
right so on the t box x engines
you will see there is an option under
html there is an option for open url
right so this is a module which will
open a url
so let's drag it into our prerequisites
folder okay
and let's close this window
and let's name this
open application
right so this is going to open our
application
and as you can see it has got these open
url right so that is the url
and we need to enter a url value here
right so let's copy this and
let's paste it here
okay so
this is our value
https www.sauce
okay
now you can use a active tab or you can
also pass browser arguments but for now
it's not required right
so
we have got our prerequisite which will
open the application we have got our
test configuration parameter set and we
have got our test case right
now the only thing remaining is to
execute the test case um again we'll be
using the scratch book to execute but
before that
let me tell you some other things which
you can do on your test cases right so
for every test case right
you will have a work state
now if you're working alone
it's fine you don't need to change it
but if you're working in a team and you
are
regularly committing your changes right
which another team member is going to
work on
then it's better to have a work state
right so
there are three work states there is
planned there is in work and there is
completed
right so
when you are working on a particular
test case you can put it in in work
right uh once you complete it you can
put it as completed right so i have
completed so i will change the workstate
here
similarly for login test i will put it
as completed
so this is just a best practice when you
are working within a team and
everyone is using the same repository
with all the test cases
you can change the work state so that
if somebody else is working on he can
know that you are still working on this
particular test okay then once it's
completed that means it's completed
okay um so our test case is ready now um
with the modules and all the different
elements now we have to run this okay
so
i've already shown you how you can run
your test case right
we can do it using the scratch book
so right click on it and click run in
scratch book
okay
as you can see it opened the application
it entered the information and clicked
on the login button okay
okay you will see everything has passed
here but
i just realized that i did made a
mistake i entered the username and
password for something else right so
it is saying username and password do
not match any user in the service
because
i need to enter this username and this
password okay so let's do that
okay standard user and then i will put
the password here
okay so now it is correct
let's go ahead and execute this again
okay so go to the main folder because
you need to execute both prerequisites
and the test case right
so
let's go here and run it in sketchbook
now you will see a browser will be
launched and it will go to the
application it will enter the
information
and click on login page so that's the
complete test case right
and if you see the scratch book
okay so it will tell you what are the
steps open url login page username
password
and everything passed right every if
anything fails it will show it here
now probably you will say that there is
one step missing which is to close the
application right so let's do that as
well
so let's create a new folder here and
we'll call it post condition right
so this will contain all our post
conditions which we want to do after
executing our test case right
so here um let's again
open our
section which is the modules section
okay
and now
what you want to do we want to search
for a module which will basically close
our window right so let's go to tbox
automation tools
here under
basic windows operations right there is
the t-box window operation so this is
the module which i want to use
okay
so
let's again put it in this view
and in post conditions
i'm just going to drag and drop this
okay
and
i'm going to name it close
application
right
now let's see what is present in these
steps okay
so here uh we need to provide it a
caption right and then we need to
provide our operation so caption um this
you need to provide it as a window name
right so there are if there are
different windows open in your browser
you need to close the proper window and
you need to provide a name which matches
that particular window name right so
since my website is swag labs right so
i'll give it swag and then i can put a
regular expression like star so it can
be any text of the swag right but this
must be present in order to
choose this particular window
and then we need to change the action
mode to select
so it will basically select the window
with this particular value okay
now the other
thing which we need to do
in this t-box window is we need to close
it right so once it's selected
so in the drop down you will see there
are different options like maximize
minimize normal right
so all the operations which you can
perform on a browser window and we need
to close that so we will select that
so these are our t-box window operation
inputs okay
now go to your folder and again try to
run this
this time around you will see after the
test case runs it will close the window
okay so as you can see there are now
three steps first is open url then login
page
and then the tbox window operation
right
so this operation is basically closing
the browser window which was opened
okay
so this is a basic test case where i
showed you how you can create a test
case how you can
scan your application create a module
with all the technical specifications or
your elements
drag those modules into your particular
test cases and then
create a proper test case flow right
so that um
your scenario would uh occur just as you
would do manually right so you will open
the application you will perform some
steps you close the application right
and then you can write all your
different test scenarios inside this
test case right
and you can have as many uh subfolders
as you like
we also talked about
the work state of each test case since
if you'll be working in a team you
should always change this workstate
right so if you're working on it change
it to in work and if you have completed
just keep it completed right so you will
see um
the icon will change as per your
workstate okay
so um
this is how you create your test case
and you also
run it in scratch book right
next section we'll see some more test
cases
and we'll also look at test case design
and other sections of tosca